Guide to the Harry Laidler Papers TAM.047
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Laidler Papers
1902-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970
TAM.047
18.25 Linear Feet (37 boxes)
Harry Wellington Laidler (1884-1970), was an economist, author, educator and socialist activist. He received his B.A. from Wesleyan University (1907) where he was one of the founders of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. He received a LL.B. from Brooklyn Law School in 1910 and a Ph.D. in political economy from Columbia in 1914. He was executive director of the League for Industrial Democracy (LID) from 1910 to 1957 and a frequent candidate for political office for the Socialist Party. He served on the New York City Council from 1940 to 1941, having been elected as a candidate of the American Labor Party, which he helped to found. The papers include radio scripts, book reviews, and correspondence (1906-1970) relating to the founding of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society and to League for Industrial Democracy (LID) activities and LID relations with the Socialist and American Labor parties, manuscripts of published and unpublished writings on a broad range of subjects, including the struggle within the LID caused by Laidler's retirement, an unpublished history of the LID, papers relating to Laidler's term (1940-1941) as a member of the New York City Council from Brooklyn, his campaigns for political office (1927-1941), the Socialist Party, the American Labor Party, the National Bureau of Economic Research, and the National Housing Conference. Includes correspondence of Norman Thomas.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Probably donated by John Laidler (Harry Laidler's son) circa 1971. The accession number associated with this gift is 1971.003. Additional materials were donated by the Laidler family in 1983.
Historical/Biographical Note
Harry Laidler, economist, author, educator and socialist activist, was born in Brooklyn, New York, February 18, 1884. He received his B.A. from Wesleyan University (1907) where he was one of the founders of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. He received a LL.B. from Brooklyn Law School in 1910 and a Ph.D. in political economy from Columbia in 1914. He was executive director of the League for Industrial Democracy (LID) from 1910 to 1957 and a frequent candidate for political office for the Socialist Party. He served on the New York City Council from 1940 to 1941, having been elected as a candidate of the American Labor Party, which he helped to found. He was the author of many books and articles on social issues.
Other Finding Aids
A more detailed folder level description is available at the Tamiment Library. However, this description does not reflect the creation of boxes 11a and 15a, and thus the folder titles are not properly aligned with the box numbers after box 11.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Wellington Laidler Photographs (PHOTOS 009)
Scope and Contents
The papers include radio scripts, book reviews, and correspondence (1906-1970) relating to the founding of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, experiments in industrial democracy, League for Industrial Democracy (LID) activities such as lecture tours, union organization, southern labor chautauquas, work with the unemployed, and LID relations with the Socialist and American Labor parties; manuscripts of published and unpublished writings on a broad range of subjects, including plans for the socialization of every aspect of society, criticism of the New Deal, and the struggle within the LID caused by Laidler's retirement; Pioneering in Social Education: The History of the LID, an unpublished book-length typescript plus research notes; and papers relating to Laidler's term (1940-1941) as a member of the New York City Council from Brooklyn, his campaigns for political office (1927-1941), Socialist Party (1919-1970), American Labor Party, National Bureau of Economic Research (1927-1982), and National Housing Conference (1962-1969). Includes correspondence of Norman Thomas.
New York (N.Y.); Unemployed -- United States.; Housing -- United States.; Socialists -- United States.; Manuscripts (document genre); Speeches.; Right and left (Political science); Scripts (documents); New York (N.Y.). City Council; National Bureau of Economic Research; National Conference on Housing (U.S.); Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; Socialist Party (U.S.); United States Labor Party; Intercollegiate Socialist Society (U.S.); League for Industrial Democracy
- Three Arrows Press (Roger Payne) Correspondence, 1940's and 1950's; 300958 (Box 1)
- Laidler Personal, Biographical, date range has not yet been determined; 300959 (Box 2)
- Laidler 75th Birthday, c.1959; 300960 (Box 3)
- Laidler 75th Birthday, c.1959; 300961 (Box 4)
- Laidler 80th Birthday, c.1964; 300962 (Box 5)
- Financial Records and Diaries, date range has not yet been determined; 300963 (Box 6)
- Laidler Correspondence, 1906-1960; 300964 (Box 7)
- Laidler Correspondence, 1961-1970; 300965 (Box 8)
- Early Manuscripts, date range has not yet been determined; 300966 (Box 9)
- Manuscripts, A-F, date range has not yet been determined; 300967 (Box 10)
- Manuscripts, G-M, date range has not yet been determined; 300968 (Box 11)
- Manuscripts, N, date range has not yet been determined; 300993 (Box 11a)
- Manuscripts, O-Social, date range has not yet been determined; 300969 (Box 12)
- Manuscripts, Socialism-Z, date range has not yet been determined; 300970 (Box 13)
- Radio Scripts, A-N, date range has not yet been determined; 300971 (Box 14)
- Radio Scripts, N-Z, date range has not yet been determined; 300972 (Box 15)
- Book Reviews, date range has not yet been determined; 300973 (Box 15a)
- Miscellaneous Writings-Articles and Book Reviews, date range has not yet been determined; 300994 (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous Writings-Articles and Book Reviews, date range has not yet been determined; 300974 (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous Writings-History of Intercollegiate Socialist Society and Notes, date range has not yet been determined; 300975 (Box 18)
- Subject Files, A-S, date range has not yet been determined; 300976 (Box 19)
- Subject Files, S-Z, date range has not yet been determined; 300977 (Box 20)
- Socialist Party (U.S.), 1939; 300978 (Box 21)
- Socialist Party (U.S.), 1940-1970; 300979 (Box 22)
- Socialist Party (U.S.), New York State, 1928-1947; 300980 (Box 23)
- Socialist Party (U.S.), New York City; Other, 1919-1970; 300981 (Box 24)
- American Labor Party, c.1930s-c.1940s; 300982 (Box 24)
- Campaigns-Alderman, City Council, Comptroller, 1931-1941; 300983 (Box 26)
- Campaigns-Governer, Senator, City Council, 1936-1942; 300984 (Box 27)
- National Bureau of Economic Research, 1927-1966; 300985 (Box 28)
- National Bureau of Economic Research and National Housing Conference, 1962-1970; 300986 (Box 29)
- "Pioneering in Social Education; The History of the League for Industrial Democracy": Typescript and Notes, date range has not yet been determined; 300987 (Box 30)
- "Pioneering in Social Education; The History of the League for Industrial Democracy": Notes, date range has not yet been determined; 300988 (Box 31)
- "Pioneering in Social Education; The History of the League for Industrial Democracy": Notes, date range has not yet been determined; 300989 (Box 32)
- Miscellaneous, B-C, 1925-1948; 300990 (Box 33)
- Miscellaneous, C-N, 1932-1954; 300991 (Box 34)
- Miscellaneous, R-U, 1919-1945; 300992 (Box 35)
- Campaign Banners (Box Shared Tamiment 023)